[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
hello everybody good evening good day to
all of you wherever you are I hope you
are all doing very well and welcome to
the latest episode of the ask widget
show
uh so let's see who all is there as
always as you know today is a live chat
q a session I'm gonna take all the
questions from the live chat so that it
gives lots of you the opportunity to
interact and ask questions so we're
gonna do that but before we do that
let's get into the let's see who all is
there
on the live chat let's see the
attendance I hear that the the IPL is on
right so I think our attendance is gonna
take a hit from that but I understand I
also have been a huge sports fan so I
totally understand that so let's see who
all is there I can see tarun khatri Once
Upon a Dime as Menor tanmaid
realm of curiosity Raja Kumar nitin
Singh Melvin Ashish Jai Dixit Martian
codename 175 Aryan peekaboo
Aman Kumar costume
feminist Slayer we are we just
crazy brain
Captain anonymous
Khan
shubham Monday
again
the bong star Amit vedant and so and so
many people so many people I will not be
able to greet you all individually but I
I greet you all collectively thank you
so much for being on the live chat on
the live stream so with that done let us
get into some questions if you have
questions
Shivam and many more okay let's let's
get into the questions now uh so if you
have questions I'm sure you all have
questions that's why you're here so
let's let's get get going with it let's
have your best questions and let us
field them
so
okay let's take this one Sumit says we
have seen the Biden President Biden is
brainless in terms of his policies and
probably so the so-called deep state is
in full control is this not similar to
Pakistan in a way yes I have remarked
upon this see the the president of the
US Mr Biden is well as as everyone can
see I mean it's it there's this Fable or
something like that the emperor has no
clothes it's like that I mean everybody
can see even a theory can see that this
guy is not in full control of his mental
capacity he's just too old
he's past a certain stage right so
clearly he's not in a position to to
administer himself let alone let alone
administering an entire nation and
Kamala Harris is clearly not competent
at all uh so and and still somebody is
running the nation right so most likely
it's what they call the establishment
and what's colloquially called The Deep
State that's what it is that's what's
running the nation the nation is not
running itself
so yeah and as we recently saw the Biden
Administration whoever that is uh wanted
to uh present dossier of Russian alleged
war crimes to the international criminal
court
and so the White House wanted to do this
and the Pentagon blocked the White House
from doing it so that demonstrates
visibly with the Pentagon has more power
way more power than the White House the
Pentagon can block the elected
government of the U.S from doing
something yeah I mean technically or you
know supposedly the U.S president is
supposed to be the boss of everyone
how can someone block the U.S president
supposedly the most powerful person in
the world man in the world it's always
been a man so clearly the Pentagon which
is the defense establishment which is
also colloqueli called The Deep state is
more powerful way more powerful than the
White House than the elected
democratically elected government which
tells us that the U.S is a democracy
kind of in name only
and there is a deeper and stronger power
at play
so the relationship between the Pentagon
and the White House is very similar to
the relationship between Rawalpindi and
Islamabad Rao Bindi is the Army
Headquarters that's where the Army is
based uh Islamabad is where the
government allegedly resides but we all
know that this Army that's in power
which means the Royal Bindi is more
powerful than Islam
and similarly we seem to have a very
similar situation in the U.S that the
Pentagon is way more powerful than the
white house so the U.S is like a super
Pakistan that's what it is but it's much
much better run and it's it's a yeah so
we know what we know the differences so
yeah interesting question that you ask
and you I I totally agree with what you
say sir
um
says what are your thoughts on the
report from the iaf that Russia will not
meet the delivery of all s-400 systems
does that mean that India will reorient
towards the West
uh India is multi-oriented multi-aligned
India is not non-aligned and India is
not an ally of Russia but yes obviously
India and Russia have a significant
amount of shared interests and
convergence in geopolitical interests
and approaches which is why India and
Russia get along so well because it just
makes sense
uh the logic of strategy says that it
makes sense for India and Russia to work
together and you know you can say they
are aligned in a lot of things now
one does hear the report that uh
uh that Russia I'm not sure it's from
the iaf or from where it is but Russia
the delivery of the s s 400 uh systems
some of them is most likely going to be
delayed there is this enormous war
effort going on in Russia there's
Manpower needed for the war effort and
resources are needed for that so that's
going to impact the delivery of s 400
systems to India it's it doesn't mean
that Russia will cancel the deliveries
we've already paid for that it means
that deliveries will most likely be
delayed by a certain amount of time
that's what it means and you know just
because your supplier isn't able to
supply what you need in a certain time
frame doesn't mean that you abandon the
I mean you you totally reorient your
strategy plus because something like
that happen no
our interests are long-term interests
you don't realize them because you get
emotional when someone can't meet a
certain requirement we know why it's why
the situation exists we understand why
that this could happen and why this is
happening so it's fine uh we definitely
will exhort and urge Russia to deliver
the system so we understand there's a
delay but deliver it as soon as possible
let us know how long how much longer it
will take and that sort of thing but it
doesn't mean that we're going to abandon
Russia and stop you know uh ask them to
cancel the deliveries and then go for
the US version which is an inferior
version and all that no that's not how
it works your our interests are
long-term interests
and we don't just uh you know turn
around and spin around on the drop of a
hat when something happens that's not
how it works right
um
okay
okay Norman says please explain the
partition of Germany after the second
world war East Germany and West Germany
okay so that gives me the opportunity to
bring out the map because we love the
map
so where is Deutschland Germany I'm sure
we all know where it is but let's Orient
ourselves this is India we go westwards
we cross the Indian subcontinent
Pakistan Afghanistan we cross our
Persian neighbors we come into the
kafka's region you go west towards there
is Ukraine and here now
east or west of Ukraine or Poland and
west of Poland you have Germany so this
is Germany and Germany was partitioned
into East Germany and West Germany after
the end of the second world war so
that's the thing that's the question
that's what the question is about so
what happened exactly how did Germany
get partitioned so what happened is this
Germany as we know were the bad guys in
during the second world war Adolf Hitler
one of the greatest evil guys that's
what the West portrays in him as and
clearly hated a lot of evil Deeds they
killed I don't know how many million
Jews and Romani people at least four
million one years so yeah and and
Germany well it was the aggressor it
tried to fight everybody at the same
time so at the end Germany lost now it
did not lose that easily it was very
hard to beat it had at some at one point
in time taken over significant almost
all of Europe it had rolled over
steamrolled to France in its Blitzkrieg
and it had launched an invasion of of
the USSR
and because of a tactical or strategic
uh you know strategic mistake that's why
they eventually lost uh and and
operation Barbarossa eventually became a
disaster because of a strategic mistake
they they went for the South instead of
going straight from for Moscow so
eventually the tide turned the Americans
entered The Fray from the west from the
from from England from the UK they
crossed over the the Normandy Landings
which are like the D-Day you know very
famous there are movies made about that
and then the inch West to eastwards from
France but the majority of the fighting
in Europe was done by the Russians and
the majority of the dying was done by
the Russians the Russians were able to
beat Germany only at the expense at the
cost of of oceans of blood they they
through incredible amounts of man you
know human lives into the meat grinder
and that's how they were able to beat
the Nazis so most of the fighting was
done by the Russians but the credit you
know the Americans take it because of
Hollywood in propaganda and all that
uh the Russians clearly are not that
good at propaganda so uh they liberated
much of Europe and what happened is that
uh the eastern part of Germany was uh
you could say liberated or conquered
Whatever by the USSR in the western part
kind of was taken over by the Allies
which is the U.S and its minions
now once uh Hitler was defeated there
was the matter of the Asia Pacific
Theater which is Japan which was dealt
with differently separately the
Americans tested two nuclear weapons on
Japanese civilians we know that
but uh so what happened is that once
Hitler was defeated Germany have a
certain portion of Germany was in the
possession of the USSR and a certain
portion of Germany was in the possession
of the U.S and its uh allies let's call
them allies
and that became kind of the partition so
as soon as the second world war ends
despite the US and the USSR being Allied
in the second world war to defeat Hitler
the Americans immediately declared that
now we are in a cold war in the USSR
other bad guys because communism is evil
and then we had the beginning of the
Cold War immediately you could say more
or less immediately after the end of the
second world war so that dividing line
in Germany became the partition line and
soon you had the Iron Curtain coming up
and you know what the entire sequence of
events
so that is how Germany got partitioned
one part of it remained with the USSR
and that ideology was applied there uh
socialism communism all that was applied
there and the other part became the
opposite of that and it took up the U.S
U.S uh style of functioning and all that
so that's how the partition happened and
as we know it it uh Germany remained uh
divided until the early 1990s until the
Berlin Wall was eventually brought down
which was actually the collapse of the
USSR itself
so that is the story my friends that is
the story now let's see who all who else
has questions
let us see let us see okay let's take
this one I can see a lot of geopolitical
questions
Melody boy says is does Russia really
love India or is it just posing because
they need allies and a big Market to
sell things to in this Ukraine war
so listen
if we look at see we have to examine
history from a certain perspective so
when we take photographs in case some of
you are into photography you will know
that you for a certain camera you have a
whole variety of lenses you can buy in
each lens serves a certain purpose you
take a subject you put it in front of
you you take a certain lens with a
certain focal length you will see a
certain perspective of the image you
take a different lens you will see a
different perspective some lenses make
it very flat some let's just give you a
blurred background and so on I will not
go into that but that's how it works
similarly when you look at history and
geopolitics the what you understand of
it depends on the lens that you're using
to take a look at it to look at it
so if you take if you use a very short
lens let's say you know very short-term
memory kind of lens then you will get a
certain picture of things if you take a
longer term perspective a longer lens
then you will see a different
perspective so the question is does
Russia really love India so if I take a
short lens and take a look at what
happened in the past five or ten years I
will get a certain perspective see uh
and it's a good perspective it's it's
very instructive so in 2017 I think or
20 whichever year it was five six years
ago seven years ago perhaps the Russians
were conducting military exercises with
Pakistan it was called the drusbah
exercises friendship in in Russian so
there was 2017 2018 2019 2020 2021 2022
if I am not mistaken but there has been
no the result 2023
and I think there's been no doubt 2022
either most likely if I'm not mistaken
you know so so how come Russia was kind
of uh being friendly with Pakistan and
and why is it not happening now why has
the why have those exercises you know
those military exercises stopped and all
that
so
the question is a very good question
and we have to look at it from a long
term perspective because that's when we
start seeing the patterns so Russia in
geopolitics there is no love there is no
love in geopolitics all right and there
is no friendship in geopolitics
geopolitics is all about self-interest
it's all about your narrow National
interest and when you have two Nations
whose national interests align and
converge it is natural for them to work
together
and when you have two Nations whose
national interests Clash then they
simply can't work together so how do you
know whether whether two Nations will
have an alignment of natural interests
or a clash of natural in national
interests one of the best ways of
understanding that is just to take a
look at the map so let me show you the
map which will give us an idea of what
is the situation
so let's take a look at the map here's
the map
so as we can see India and China have a
significant long shared border because
we allowed China to conquer Tibet and
occupy Tibet in 1950. our great prime
minister the group magnificent Mr narrow
did that so India and China have a long
and demarcated border which makes India
and China
it makes it impossible for Indian China
to be allies
when two large Nations have a shared
border common border it means that they
can never be allies and they will always
have some kind of tension and some kind
of hostility similarly the Russians and
the Chinese have a long border which
tells you that the Russians and the
Chinese are also not natural allies
their natural adversaries now India in
Russia don't have a shared border India
and Russia both want a stable and secure
Central Asia India and Russia both see
China as an adversary for very good
reason I mean I'll not go into the
history of the Russia China thing but
yeah it's there
so from these perspectives if you look
at all of this from the big picture
perspective from the long lens of the
past hundred years
then you will see that Russia and India
are actually natural allies we will not
use the term Ally
okay but it's kind of like that it's
kind of like a you know a de facto
Unwritten Alliance kind of thing in in
certain ways we we try to keep it under
wraps you could say so there's no love
here
love happens when there is shared blood
or shared culture okay that's when love
exists so when it comes to the nations
of the Indian subcontinent yeah we could
actually say that there is love in some
sense I would not say there is love
between India and Pakistan
but clearly one could have an
affectionate perspective from India's
perspective towards Nepal or Sri Lanka
or Bhutan
or or Myanmar
and well if the other nations behave we
will be affectionate towards them as
well so love only exists when you have
shared blood or shared culture when it
comes to Russia we don't have shared
blood and we don't have shared culture
either but we have a strong convergence
of national interests so Russia does
feel the pressure right now because of
the Ukraine war obviously it feels the
pressure and it does need allies it does
need a huge market for selling oil
because that is what relieves the
pressure from Russia so yes it does need
that for that from that perspective
India is something they really need so
yeah it's a great thing for them but
it's not like they are playing a
short-term game it's a long-term game in
India and Russia are going to be aligned
for the long term for this entire
Century one could imagine if not more
so that's the deal there's no love
there's no love in geopolitics there are
alliances and alliances typically are
temporary and even enmities are
temporary but in some cases these
alliances can be long term and enmities
can be long term when you have this this
border thing okay I think that was a
reasonably long explanation let's take
some other questions
all right
um
okay says what's the geographical
experience of Arya worth is it just
Northern India the whole of the Indian
subcontinent look it's the whole of the
Indian subcontinent uh that's what it is
uh even
I this is the problem right they have
divided into India into North India and
South India and Aryan and rubidium so we
all see everything from that these
perspectives only North India versus
South India the whole of the Indian
subcontinent was called Jammu dweep and
Arya that's what it was in the Indian
subcontinent included present-day
Pakistan the temporary nation and also
Gandhara which is present day
Afghanistan even when SRI chingas Khan
came into India pursuing jalaluddin
the border between India and Central
Asia were somewhere was somewhere in
Tajikistan okay there is a there is
there was some what hot gays or
something it was called I don't remember
right now but yes so so that's the ex
that's the geographical expanse of the
Indian subcontinent it was the entirety
of jambudweep or Arya the whole
subcontinent not just North India
so I I understand where this question
comes from and yeah it's it's see the
fact that lots of people have these
questions is a good thing they are they
are wondering what they've been taught
is right or not and what we have been
taught is a lot of lies a whole bunch of
Lies so what we need all of us my
friends is to learn the art of in the
science of critical thinking
we have been taught what to think
instead of being taught how to think
when you come across a textbook how do
you know whether it contains facts or
opinions or a mix of both and how do you
know that so and so paragraph is a fact
and so and so paragraph is an opinion
that is where critical thinking comes in
that is something we all need to learn
and you know I mean I could go deep into
it it will take me at least at least an
hour to explain that but yeah so we all
need to figure out in our own way
how to think
so I actually I believe I know how to
think but I I really would like to urge
and encourage and exhort all of you
please
try and analyze your thought process and
try to figure out how it can be improved
like I say keep raising your standards
am I a dhoni fan there's a match going
on now right Mumbai Indians and children
were in the Chennai Super Kings yes and
dhoni is CSK yeah of course I'm a dhoni
fan of course I mean he's one of the
greatest uh cricketers we've had one of
the greatest captains we've had great
guy I mean
I mean what's not to admire so yes of
course I'm a dhoni fan
um let's see what else what else do we
have
um
ABCD what your thoughts your views on
Ashoka University should I join it I um
I regret that I don't really know much
about this uh institution I so yeah I
won't be able to answer because I don't
have much knowledge about it but yeah
you should do your due diligence and if
it is good according to your Viewpoint
you should certainly join it
which team do I support in the IPL I
haven't watched a single IPL match this
year
uh you know whoever plays well I will
I'll support them uh I've never had a
favorite as such
um
I remember I've watched the first IPL I
think it was in 2007 or 2008 and the
next year they'd played in South Africa
because the elections were there
uh which year was this 20 2014 was 2000
yeah 2008 I think was the first IPL yeah
anyhow so um
I don't have any specific favorite team
I haven't watched a single match this
year thus far
um so yeah that's far nothing but if if
some team plays well and catches my
attention and grabs Me by you know by
the throat here and then I'll certainly
support that all right let's see what
else do we have lots of questions of
course
um
uh
India helped turkey by launching
operation Dost but still turkey is very
much anti-india then why did India help
turkey pre-assured don't call me naive
no absolutely not I will not call you
naive it's a very good question we have
to ask these questions so that we
understand the world better all right so
uh yes India turkey was struck by two
horrific earthquakes very powerful
earthquakes it caused a huge amount of
Devastation in the nation lots of people
died sadly very unfortunate and India
was one of the First Responders without
being asked we went ahead and launched
these operation Operation those we sent
uh teams of medical personnel to Turkey
lots and lots of equipment and supplies
to Turkey
um we set up field hospitals over there
we we sent search and rescue teams with
with the trained personnel and and teams
with dogs as well so we did a whole lot
I think they were one of the major
responders and helpers for turkey
but turkey is still very much anti-india
yes a biggest surprise so why did India
help turkey so you know
there are reasons why we do things
listen if there is a crocodile
uh listen I learned to use the word
snake here
I'm just giving an example okay let's
let's not take it personally anybody if
there is anybody from Turkey here listen
I have absolutely nothing against turkey
I think Turkish people are actually very
interesting people very fun people all
right nothing against turkey at all but
overall India and turkey are not aligned
turkey is geopolitical alignment is with
essentially India's enemy Pakistan so
let's it's not a personal thing people
to people I'm sure we're all friends but
Nation relation we are adversaries
so we have to understand that if you go
ahead and help crocodile it doesn't mean
that if the crocodile gets an
opportunity it'll you will not try to
eat you right
so then the question is why did India do
this so India is building a track record
as a responsible nation and a
responsible member of the International
Community a nation that sets certain
standards and behaves in a certain
manner
and even helps enemies when it's
required so once you and you have to do
this consistently you do this this
this strategy this Doctrine whatever you
want to call it only started sometime
around 2014. before that India was not a
global geopolitical player at all it was
not even a local power India was not
respected anywhere in the world now
India is building a track record of a
certain kind of behavior
internationally so in the future when
India Rises India is Rising by the way
once we are at let's say a 10 trillion
dollar economy we're going to have a
certain amount of Economic and Military
muscle and we want to use it in a way
that is non-abrasive and we want to get
our things done but we also want to tell
the world that we are a responsible
nation and we you need not fear us
eventually we will it will reach a stage
once the nation reaches a certain size
economically and militarily people start
wondering should we fear them that's
what happens so and if everyone fears
you then then what happens is what
happens what's happening with China
China is kind of isolated yeah sure they
are able to they still have a lot of
influence they still have not a lot of
money to throw around which buys them
influence and that's why they're able to
do things but overall everybody fears
China everybody fears China
everyone in Asia around China let's take
a look at the map once again everybody
look at China's neighbors everyone fears
them no one trusts them but of course
there will be enticed by the money that
China is able to spend so when India is
rising we have to ensure that we build a
track record that you know will
ensure that people that other nations
don't fear us
and it also helps us to counter U.S
propaganda
the Americans in the west overall they
have been trying to portray India in a
certain manner
authoritarian Nation some some stupid
journalists use the word fascist
undemocratic all that so when India does
these things it kind of you know
it it
it hurts these fake narratives and it
kind of destroys these fake narratives
so there are multiple reasons why India
is doing this for overall it's for image
building image building is called Soft
power right so it doesn't cost a whole
lot of money from India's perspective to
go and help turkey
right if you if you take a reasonably
large city in India and the amount of
money it takes to run that City for one
day
I'm sure we did not have to spend even
that much for the operation those in
Turkey yeah a few few aircraft heavy
aircraft is in there if you Personnel I
don't know
and uh our people were there I don't
know how long a few weeks or something
so overall I don't think it cost a lot
of money but it it uh creates a certain
image of India in front of the world and
among the Turkish people who were helped
by us it definitely builds Goodwill and
they'll remember us they'll remember
what we did for them in their time of
need desperate need so these are the
reasons why we do it we don't expect
anything in return but we are building a
certain narrative and certain in a
certain image of ourselves and a track
record for ourselves that is what's
happening so even when you had the
pandemic coronavirus pandemic we sent
vaccines all across the world especially
to poor Nations and Nations that could
not afford the expensive American
vaccines that that don't really work
there are terrible vaccines our vaccine
probably is the best vaccine out there
so we send these vaccines we do not sell
them we sent them for free the Americans
will sell you stuff and then they will
call it Aid you know that's the
hypocrisy
they will sell you stuff for extremely
for a lot of money
and then they will say we are aiding you
they they call their military sales of
Taiwan Aid
you know so India did not do that we
sent it for free so once again we are
building a track record as a responsible
Nation as a good Nation as a benevolent
Nation it's going to help us in the long
run that's why we do it
Martian says what do you think about
nostradamus's prediction of World War
III I had a book of Nostra by by not I
mean which was about Nostradamus I found
it very interesting
I mean it seemed to predict the 9 11
attacks in the U.S a city at 45 degrees
fire comes from the sky very interesting
uh it did also predict Napoleon and
history
Napoleon seems like sounds like Napoleon
yes and history sounds like Hitler
so it it's It's Curious you know I mean
some of it was very striking and very
interesting to me so I don't know what
if if there is an invention of World War
III in that or not there are these
quatrains in that he writes in which he
writes uh you know this verses in old
French
uh so yeah I haven't I don't remember it
was too long I mean it's been so long
it's been like 20 years since I you know
held that book in my hands so I don't
remember what the predictions were like
about world war three if at all
I it looked I think it sounded like it
was there was a prediction that India
will rise in the 21st century and become
a you know a great power or something a
superpower perhaps so I don't quite
remember but I I found it very
interesting that this guy who lived
before Napoleon in history
Hitler was able to write about that is
it a complete coincidence or is there
something more to it I still don't know
but I think it's very interesting
okay
um
all right let's see uh they just says
why do afghanistanis claim that The
Vedas originated there do they I'm sure
people make all kinds of claims I I
suppose some of the Afghans would claim
that The Vedas are originated there I
think everybody wants to own the
birthplace or the of the of The Vedas
right
I remember there was this uh General
retired General on Twitter a few years
ago who said that uh The Vedas were
written in Punjab because the Saraswati
used to flow through Punjab with the
Saraswati flowed through the entire
subcontinent uh the western part of the
subcontinent so
um
so we don't we don't quite know where
The Vedas were written where they were
written within the sacred land of
parathavash or even we know that and
most likely the Saraswati is called the
the goddess of wisdom and knowledge so
most likely The Vedas were written
somewhere along the bank banks of the
Saraswati the great Saraswati river
which no longer is with us she has left
us because we are so stupid yeah uh and
clearly the Sarasota did not flow
through Afghanistan
uh the Saraswati flowed from the
Himalayas all the way into the uh sea of
saurashtra
the so-called Arabian Sea and if you
look at the undersea map topological map
of the Indian Ocean you can actually see
ancient drainage channels of rivers that
no longer exist including the Saraswati
so uh let's put the map on the screen
not like this but like this yes so the
saraswatis it it drained somewhere maybe
along the mouth of the mouth of Gujarat
you know Gujarat looks like a face so
somewhere here somewhere here is where
the Saraswati used to drain out into the
into the Indian Ocean and she eventually
started drying out that's why we had the
Run of Kutch that was created in the
Thar Desert as well
and now she is simply a seasonal
intermittent river called the kaggarh
so The Vedas were most likely written on
the banks of the Saraswati so clearly
that that was not Afghanistan
Afghanistan was northern part of India
Gandhara but obviously some everyone
wants to own The Vedas everybody wants
to claim you know some kind of
connection or ownership and in
Afghanistan obviously we know that their
their culture and everything has changed
they are no longer uh they no longer uh
practice Indian culture and Indian
religions and yet there is some some
connection obviously because they're
they're still after all genetically
ethnically our kin right the pashtoons
I'm not talking about the the other
ethnicities the tajiks sure the pashto's
mostly sure but not the the the whoever
else the other ethnic makes its out
there so uh so if they are in the if
some of them claim it it's it's because
they may feel a certain connection
perhaps to India whether they
acknowledged it or not
but well they also can claim to be
uh part of our heritage because I'm sure
their ancestors also at some point in
time we know that they were all
part of Indian culture not anymore
unfortunately okay this question has to
be there
Pok isn't it the right time to take back
I I get this question like 27 times at
least per day in in the comments uh no
this is not the right time to take back
P okay maybe in six months maybe maybe
in two years maybe before 2024 or maybe
in a decade but soon enough see as we
know Pakistan is a temporary Nation we
have to have a bit of patience we we
will win we will regain be okay
eventually in the long run the entirety
of of an undivided India will be unified
again eventually not now not not next
week not next month eventually in the
next 50 years 100 years because right
now it's it's not appropriate or it's
not good for us to to reincorporate
those regions into India because of a
variety of reasons
uh so it's not the right time to take
back be okay when is the right time to
dig quick be okay
the right time to win is when Victory is
inevitable
the best way of winning is to is to win
without firing a single shot
so we have to engineer a situation in
which Pok
Ed automatically on its own comes back
to us without us firing a single bullet
a single shot or losing a single life
that's how it has to be so that is the
ideal way in which we want to take back
poke it should just fall into our our
arms that's how it should be so this is
not the right time to take that P okay
the time will come patience
right
um
what else what else what else what it is
what else do we have
ah this question
says I wanted to know are Baloch is pure
Iranian race or are they mixed Indian
Iranian that is where
pure Indian proper Indian if you see
their coins and all the swastikas and
and thresholds and all that and their
name also was Paratha Raja so it's
clearly Indian no ethnicity wise
the Iranians aren't that different from
us
yes the genetics are kind of weird I
mean there's very little r1a over there
the the para the petroleum have to group
I think it's more of r1b or more of R2
or something so it's it's clearly very
very close to India but if you look at
the pro the detailed genetic profile of
Iranian people you will see a lot of
affinity with with the Turks Azerbaijan
and uh the what other places do we see
Azerbaijan and and
Iraq turkey Etc so what happened
unfortunately in the about
1300 or so 1400 years ago is Iran was
overrun by the Arabs
and they lost their sovereignty
uh and uh eventually you know all these
uh Invaders came and settled down and
that's why there was this ethnic mixing
so Iranians many Iranians are not that
close genetically and ethnically to
Indians anymore the pure Iranians are
essentially the same as Indians but I
don't know how many of them actually
still exist if there is such a thing as
a pure ethnicity or whatever so if you
if you take the typical stereotypical
proper Iranian it's a person with light
brown skin brown eyes and dark hair
that's how it is but you will see some
Iranians who have got you know blonde
hair and and blue eyes and almost white
skin or whatever so those are not the
real Iranians actually so when it comes
to the Balochi people they are pure
Indian
okay they're pure Indian and if you mix
Indians and Iranians you get Indians
only so that's what the balochis are
their language sounds Indian more than
Persian way more Indian than Persian
their culture is more like their culture
of saurashtra the way of the way they
the kind of clothes they wear and all
that and so Russia anyway is almost next
total Balochistan if it's the map so
Balochi people are ethnically
Indian culturally I'm not sure where
they are right now they're kind of
somewhere in between but ethnically
Indian historically Indian their
Heritage is Indian uh but yeah their
history is tragic
history in the past since
1948 is tragic and even before that the
past few hundred years before that it
was still tragic let's not fall okay
all right
is Europe really a separate continent
well let's find out where is the map
what does the map tell us
so let's take a look at the continents
straya is a continent stria Australia uh
Antarctica is a continent see as you can
see there's ocean all around it it's
totally isolated so is Antarctica Africa
is also connected to Asia by this small
sliver of land which has now been sliced
open by the Suez Canal also ways then
you have the Strait of Gibraltar which
which separates Africa from Europe so
Africa is a separate continent now you
have the Americas which are connected by
this very thin sliver of land through
Panama but you clearly have two distinct
continents North and South America now
let's take a look at Europe and Asia do
you see any division anywhere
there is no division it's a single land
mass it's an enormous land mass
smaller than Africa for I'm not sure if
it's small than Africa uh so it's it's a
single land mass
so it's a single continent you could
call it Eurasia or whatever so why is
this why is Europe considered to be
different continent and why is Asia
considered to be separate Europe
actually is a tiny little part of
Eurasia so the division is totally
imaginary and artificial the Europeans
once they became World conquerors in the
past 500 500 years started imagining
that there they were somehow superior to
the rest of the rest of humanity so they
said that our uh the place where we live
is a separate continent of its own just
because we are better than all of you
right so the so the separation between
Europe and Asia
is entirely imaginary and fictional you
know
in cities in urban places in India we
have these gangs of dogs who live
everywhere see the Indian dog has been
part of our life part of our history and
culture for thousands of years I'm sure
we are the ones who first domesticated
the dog from the wolf
so dogs they live in these
families or gangs or whatever you want
to call them and they have these
imaginary boundaries
you know each each pack of dogs
has its own territory
and you will have territories that are
adjoining each other there are imaginary
boundaries and if a dog from a
neighboring territory crosses over to
your territory this imaginary line then
all the dogs from this side will start
barking at him get out go back
so these boundaries are entirely
imaginary similarly the boundary between
Europe and Asia is just like those
boundaries that dogs have completely
fictional completely imaginary
right let us see
surinder Singh rajput says is pole shift
real so we have
our planet has poles let's let's go to
the map
so here is our planet the North Pole is
up here in the Arctic Ocean and the
South Pole is within the continent of
Antarctica and the Earth spins as we can
see meow it spins like a cricket ball
when you are spinning it yeah
so the axis of the spin
is the two ends of that are the North
Pole in the South Pole so those are the
axes so that's the rotational axis of
the earth and that's the North Pole in
the South Pole but we also have magnetic
pools so the Earth has a magnetic field
because inside the earth there is this
hot uh
below the crust in the mantle of the
earth you have a magma layer which is
molten rock and be beneath that if you
go further deep inside you have molten
metal
and at the at the center there's a solid
metal core which is not molded in molten
it's solid so because you have extremely
hot molten metal inside the planet which
is swirling around that activity it is
ionized I'm sure at some points some
some of it is ionized they will have you
will have electrical charges and it's
flowing so these moving electrical
charges they create a magnetic field so
the Earth has a magnetic field it has
two magnetic poles the North Pole and
the South Pole
now the the North Pole and the South
Pole this magnetic the magnetic poles
are created by the movement of the inner
liquid ocean of metal inside the earth
now this movement keeps changing from
time to time so every few thousand or
hundred thousand years the poles they
shifts they flip
to the North Pole so the North Pole
becomes a South Pole kind of you know
and the South Pole becomes the North
Pole so this is the real phenomenon and
we can see the traces of this in the
geological record
yeah so pole shift is real and it will
have certain consequences it could be
detrimental confidence
consequences as well it is something
that is real it will eventually happen
the north magnetic pole will suddenly
become the South magnetic pole and it
seems that some some reports that we
hear say that it the process may be
already under motion perhaps let's see
so it is indeed real it's it's a
physical
phenomenon for sure
all right
um
who could be the next foreign minister
well we have a wonderful foreign
minister one of the most competent
foreign ministers we've ever had Dr Jai
Shankar why do we want to think of the
next foreign minister I would like to
see Dr jayashankar be the foreign
minister for another five years at least
after 2024.
so yeah and so so I don't know yeah I
would like to see Dr Jai Shankar
continue for the foreseeable future
because he's not an old man I mean he's
reasonably Young
and I I don't know I mean I see him
easily doing the job for under 10 years
if he wants to
okay
uh
ubendran says what if we tell China that
if they keep causing border issues we
will stop following the one China policy
how will China react to it listen
uh try and understand it like this
let's say you have a tiger and a cat
okay a very good example
so the tiger says I have a certain
territory and I will grab other people's
territories
and then I will say that you have to
follow the one tiger policy my territory
is is one single policy a single
territory and everybody has to follow
the policy the cat says I will not
follow it anymore from tomorrow
what's going to happen who is more
powerful we have to see it that way
that's how it works in geopolitics Size
Matters power matters it's not about
being polite and being nice that's not
how geopolitics Works geopolitics is
pure power place the larger your economy
the larger the military the more
powerful you are and the more you can
get done
so you can insist that other nations
follow the one in China policy if you're
powerful enough and the others have to
do it
so it's not about words strong words
that doesn't work
s don't work you should be in a position
to walk the talk
so right now India need not do all that
right now India should hide its capacity
capabilities and buy this type and work
really hard and when the time is right
we will instead of telling them that we
will do this we will do that we'll
actually do it that's how it is
chaitanya says what's your opinion on
Pali person similarities listen Pali is
a language that came out of Sanskrit
it's an upper branchial language
and Persian is another language that
came out of Sanskrit it's also an
Aboriginal language yeah uh old portion
old person was a
very similar to Sanskrit the the person
that was spoken during the time of the
haksha Manish Dynasty the AKA minute
Dynasty during the time of cruise
which is Cyrus the Great and
so at that time if you see the old
person that they wrote using the QD form
script it sounded like you know I'm kind
of
kind of mispronounced Sanskrit
um so today's the Persian language is a
descendant of that language so clearly
there will be similarities between the
Persian language and various Indian
languages uh Persian people Iranian
people who come to India let's say for
studies and they stay in India for a
couple of years they pick up Hindi
extremely easily then they can speak
Hindi like a native
and I'm sure that if Indians were to go
to Persia we can we could pick up the
language very easily because there are
there are there are very close
similarities lots of similarities
so it's not a surprise whatsoever
okay
let's see is a more recent questions
um
General says do you think Bharat should
procure state of the art fifth
generation fighter aircraft or wait for
amca if yes which aircraft would be the
best pick for iaf the F-35 the f-32
Raptor or the su-57 I think the best way
forward is to be completely
completely indigenous manufacturing it's
not an easy process I understand I agree
it's not easy but it's worthwhile
because you're gonna build up you're
gonna build the capability to do so many
things if you can Master the art of
Designing and building and testing and
perfecting one aircraft it you can that
the same capabilities can be applied to
a whole lot of different kinds of
aircraft
the AMC will take I don't know until
what time 29 2032 somewhere around that
time maybe another eight years let's say
another 10 years let's say it's fine
it's worth it so in the meanwhile maybe
we can buy some aircraft as a stop Gap
measure measure uh if you buy American
aircraft you have to give up a lot of
your sovereignty you have to ensure
there is a lot of interoperability you
have to sign certain agreements and open
up your spectrum and it's it's not
something you want to do you don't want
the Americans to start to start snooping
on your networks and all those things
the Americans don't even spare their own
allies the the Australians for instance
when they sold the Oscar as the fa-18
super Hornets those Hornets those
aircrafts were completely useless
because the Americans had kind of
disabled them
um you know the iff system and all that
if Friend or Foe and the target
acquisition system all that so we don't
want to buy American fighter planes the
F-35 and they will not sell you they
have to have 22 either F-35 I'm sure
they will be willing to sell it for the
right price maybe 150 million dollars
per piece or whatever so yeah I think if
we have to buy something in the in the
short term as an interim measure we
could go with the Rafal
and if the Russians can you know give us
a good deal like tot transfer of
Technology then we could look into the
su-57 most likely it's going to be the
Rafal not the F-16 F-18 or whatever the
F 22 F-35 most likely than a file
um so yeah that's that's what I think
should happen we should be Atman we
should invest in our own manufacturing
capabilities in prowess and we have
extremely talented people so it's
certainly very feasible we should wait
for the amca and we should once the AMC
is out we should start building other
kinds of aircraft so that's what we need
to do my friends
okay
yeah this question I mean we don't have
evidence right uh chirag says is it true
that King Vikram Aditya had the largest
Empire which was ever probably uh bigger
than the modern Empire are there any
evidences of it so our archaeologists
have found no evidence because they've
not searched for it and they claim that
the King
was a complete myth
evidence may be lying around but if you
don't look for it then you will never
find it
and if you find it you can claim it
something or the other so we don't know
so for me I I rely on evidence hard
evidence and I am not going out there in
the field looking for evidence right so
I have to rely on what the
archaeologists are telling us and
clearly I am sure you all know that uh
we all understand that our
archaeologists are not entirely properly
motivated and they're not some of them
are good clearly some of them are good
but most of them I don't even know what
they're doing you know
so uh in the absence of evidence I would
say I don't know
we don't have evidence of how large the
empire was we don't even know for sure
when he lived most likely at the
beginning
for sure but uh we don't have the
evidence because our archaeologists have
either hidden the evidence or they have
not tried to find it at all so in the
absence of evidence I cannot offer you a
proper answer because I don't have one
I can offer you some wild speculation in
the imagination but what's the point of
that right it's not going to help you or
me so my answer is I don't know because
there is no evidence
in the future there could be evidence
and one would hope to find it as soon as
possible
saurabh asks what's the source of modern
numerals Indian or Arabic the Arabs
learned the innumerals from India the
decimal system the numerals all of it
came from India I think it's it's a
no-brainer it's it the the source is
India not Arabia
uh
okay
uh what are the question did I have here
we are Spartan bhagava says how much did
the turkic genocide of India and selling
of Indians into slavery outside of India
affect India's genetic diversity
so um the turkic genocide of India it
kind of it was a significant you know I
mean it's the worst genocide ever
perpetrated anywhere in the world so
India's population over about 500 years
or so roughly fell by 80 million
so you had people being born
at the regular rate
so the population should have stayed the
same or should it should have grown but
it declined by 80 million over a number
of centuries so if you do the math
properly and think it out properly it
means that hundreds of millions of
Indians were killed that's what it means
so maybe minimum figure is 100 million
maximum figure is maybe 500 million over
five centuries or so which means a
million a year which is something they
were doing routinely routinely right so
it did affect India's genetic pool
diversity whatever we want to call it
selling of Indians into slavery outside
of India was something that was
happening on a very large scale
it was typically women and children and
obviously men who had certain skills
Artisans uh stone masons Architects
musicians all that
so it did not affect India's genetic
diversity within the Indian subcontinent
but it spread Indian genetics outside
India you go to emn or you look at
images of yemeni people they look just
like Indians but they speak Arabic
their culture is completely Arabic but
they look many of them look exactly like
Indians there are lots of people in
Saudi Arabia who look strikingly Indian
there are people in Iraq who look Indian
some people have been even claiming the
Saddam Hussein was a rajput right Saddam
Hussein
that he was a rajput I mean if you look
at Saddam Hussein it does kind of look
somewhat Indian little bit same kind of
skin color similar facial features and
all that
um
so clearly Indian genetics spread across
the uh the turkic and Arabic world
right so it kind of spread India's
genetics in a very tragic and
unfortunate manner in the turkic and
Arabic world for sure
so that's what happened
surge ant says are Romani people and the
country of Romania related well it's it
sounds like there should be a relation
but it's not quite the case if you look
at the nation of Romania and if you look
at the population demographics and all
that I would say about roughly 10
percent of the population of Romania is
of Romani origin Gypsy Indian origin
yeah
um and yet the nation of Romania the
name doesn't come from the Romani people
so it's it's entirely it's entirely a
coincidence the Romani people are
related to India and they're not uh they
were not the founders of Romania and the
name Romania doesn't come from there so
the relation is is entirely the the
similarity of the name is entirely
coincidental there's not a genuine
connection there
Hitachi says is there any benefit of
learning Japanese as an Indian which
foreign language should one learn
according to you and that's well if you
want to interact with Japanese people
and if you want to maybe go and visit
Japan maybe stay in Japan for a while if
you're doing business with Japanese
people or if you're interacting with
them on a regular basis it makes a lot
of sense to learn Japanese it's always
fun to learn new languages
so uh that would be the benefit in case
you need to have interactions with
Japanese people that would be
advantageous for you uh the other
question is what which foreign language
should one learned according to you well
it look who am I to tell you what
language to learn I can tell you what
Indian language to learn I will insist
that everybody should learn Sanskrit so
that's what I can tell you about Indian
languages when it comes to foreign
languages it's entirely up to you it's
your choice whatever you find
interesting some people find
Japanese interesting some people want to
learn French someone learn Italian
we all speak English
why not Swahili Swahili is from Kenya
and South Africa and southern Africa or
what about Russian or what about
um
what else people want to learn Mandarin
these days Mandarin which is which is
Chinese
I think one should try and learn
Mongolian if somebody has the interest I
don't know see it's entirely up to you
it's your choice personally it's
entirely your personal choice
um
so yeah I mean if you when you learn a
foreign language it takes time it's kind
of a long process unless you are
completely immersed in an environment
where only that language is spoken in
that case you can learn a language in
like a week if you are in that sort of
environment if you really apply yourself
so I don't think there's any specific
language which should be learned I think
it's entirely a personal choice
okay
um
what other questions do we have
uh Suraj says I recently visited
Malaysia and there were many occasions
where they did not treat Indian people
very well is there any reason behind
this I do not know
um
if you look at the relations between
India and Malaysia from a geopolitical
government to government perspective the
relations aren't very good because of
certain provocations that Malaysia has
done in the past few years
um in India did retaliate at some point
in time by stop by by halting the
purchase of Malaysian palm oil India
most likely was the biggest market for
that so that kind of hurt Malaysia's
economy so the relations aren't very
good between India and Malaysia and it's
because of the attitude of the Malaysian
government it was the regime of mahatira
Muhammad I believe which which was the
uh culprit at that time mahadur Muhammad
himself is of Indian origin by the way I
think from his mother's several father
said one from Kerala
um
so uh I don't know what the attitude is
in Malaysia towards Indians but you are
reporting that there was some occasion
or many occasions where they did not
treat Indian people very well so either
it's because of the geopolitical thing
that uh India and Malaysia the
governments don't get along very well or
maybe it's a cultural or religious thing
because our culture and religion is
different from theirs I mean overall our
culture and religion is our own in
Malaysia it's it's entirely different so
maybe that could be the for the possible
reason I don't really know because I
have not really paid attention to
Malaysia it's not that important a
nation I'm sure it's very important for
the people who live there but from my
perspective I have not really being been
paying attention to it too much
says China will be renaming cities in
our matcha Pradesh how should we reply
to it can we rename the regions in Tibet
if yes what's stopping India like I said
cat versus tiger right now let us be the
cat and let the tiger roar okay we are
also not a very small cat if the tiger
tries to come into our territory we know
what to do with the Tiger but words
don't really matter real actions matter
if the Chinese actually try and come and
try to take our territory we know
exactly what to do right now they're
simply provoking us and trying to uh lay
the foundation for a future
opportunity that they may get in the
future if they do get then they will
they will like to claim it uh so right
now India should uh let's say
officially Lodge
a protest
at at most
and apart from that we don't need to the
government needs not need does not need
to do anything what we can do is we can
publish our own Maps of Tibet with the
original Tibetan names or Sanskrit names
that's what we could do nobody is
stopping us the the citizens of India
from doing that
so uh that's how we can reply from it
reply to it
from the government's perspective the
reply is going to be response if any is
going to be very measured very calm and
we're not going to give a knee-jerk
response because that's what they would
like you know to make us seem like we
are rattled so the government is going
to have a very calm measured response
but we the citizens can do whatever we
want so why don't we some of us I mean
there are lots of people watching some
of you will have Photoshop skills and
whatever graphic design skills why don't
you create a map
of Chinese occupied Tibet with Sanskrit
names or Tibetan names
that'll be fun and let's let's uh
promote those maps and put them on
social media that's what we could do
what's stopping us nobody's stopping us
yeah so we can rename religions regions
and Tibet we can even rename regions in
Yunnan because Yunnan itself is not
really Chinese even even inner Mongolia
is on Chinese even Manchuria is not
really Chinese Han Chinese so yeah
there's a whole can of worms in there
when it comes to China
right what else
[Applause]
um
dungar Singh Johan asks did ancient
India have any stimulant or caffeinated
drinks before coffee and tea were
introduced by the British in the 19th
century
so yes
coffee for sure came from the Middle
East maybe from Arabia
uh tea could have been in India before
that if I have not really researched the
origins of tea and when it was
introduced into India but uh so the
question is the real question is did
India have any such stimulants that were
consumed so I think uh some some Indians
have this habit of chewing Beetle leaves
and Beetle nuts and all that that I
believe gives the kind of a kick or
something I've never done it myself uh
so that was there
I am sure tobacco must have existed and
people would have chewed tobacco
uh I'm not sure where tobacco came from
and if it is something that that grows
in Eurasia
but if it was there then that could be a
possibility but if you go to The Vedic
times there is obviously the mentions of
us of somaras so somras was a stimulant
it was not an intoxicant it was a
stimulant it's something that uh
Warriors would drink consume before they
went into battle it gave them this you
know
extra energy it was like an energy drink
of some kind it was called Somers and
there's so many copious references to
Somers in the rigveda so yeah that's the
original stimulant that our ancestors
had but we kind of have lost track of
what it was
um it used to be stocks that were
oppressed and the juices to come out of
that and that was consumed but which
plant it was or tree it was we kind of
seem to have lost the understanding of
knowledge of what it was one of the
candidates is ephedra ephedra is is a
it's plant that grows in the Northern
parts of India in Jammu and Kashmir in
Himachal Pradesh Etc
and also in Central Asia
so that kind of you know
kind of ties in with the claims of the
Aryan Invasion Theory so that's
something that people like to cite but
there is no evidence that ephedra is the
plant in question the Soma plant so the
Soma plant its identity has been lost so
we don't quite know but yes it was the
original intoxicant in India
your views on the removal of mughals
from ncert text box I you know
history should be factual
I am very clear about this and if bad
things happened we need to be taught
those bad things so that we can confront
reality
and only when we confront reality and
confront our past will we be able to
move past that and go into a bright
future
because right now what we are what we
have
is that we are not taught certain things
of course in the textbooks they are over
glorifying the mughals or glorifying
them
there will be simply one chapter about
the maratha history of India about the
great shivaji Maharaja then there will
be like one I'm sorry not one chapter
one paragraph one paragraph and there
will be one paragraph about Subhash
Chandra Bose and there'll be entire
chapters about the mughals
so that is the strong what we need is a
balanced treatment and we need to be
taught about what these people actually
did to India they were not some great
benevolent rulers they were horrific
barbarians who did or Untold atrocities
in India so that's what needs to be
taught unfortunately we try to brush all
these bad things into the carpet because
you know secularism and what not I don't
know what it is
um so I would say that we should not
remove any part of history from
textbooks but we should keep it but we
should approach it factually the true
facts have to be put forth and I think
you know
it's it's politically not expedient at
all and very dangerous to do such things
they keep on pushing it to the future
future Generations will do it so we're
gonna get we're gonna stay stuck
where we are unfortunately so my view is
very clear history has to be factual you
should not delete or expunge
any part of History we should be taught
that that's what I
very strongly believe
okay
um
what else do we have
Dr Jason supremacist says do you think
what do
what you think should what do you think
should the government replace the great
mahatma's picture with this picture on
our rupee notes I think we have given
the Mahatma the the Mr Gandhi Mr
Mohandas Gandhi uh many decades of our
time
I think
we you know it's time to move on
we have so many great people
who have
walked the great land of India and who
have served the motherland
so why not give them also
the recognition and the honor
and and the tribute that we can pay to
them by
by having their
picture on the currency notes so one of
the candidates that comes to mind
immediately is
the other I can think of is uh
chatrapati shivaji Maharaja
we know what he looked like because we
have portraits of him and we also had
obviously many great Kings and rulers in
the past so whose portraits we don't
have so it's kind of hard to put them on
currency notes so I would imagine it
will be more recent historical figures
who would have to go on his on rupee
notes
um so yeah maybe it's time I don't know
it's up to the government to do that but
the problem is that the government will
not do such a thing because it's
dangerous it's dangerous because he's
going to lose votes most people still
believe that Mr Mr Gandhi was a great
Mahatma
he was a politician
right but he has been marketed as a
Mahatma that's a kind of brand building
that has been done
and that's still politically very
convenient
so it won't happen anytime anytime soon
it looks like
rishabh says is it possible to become an
athlete boxing powerlifting
weightlifting Etc and study or do a job
at the same time it's certainly possible
to to look
it's certainly possible to stay fit you
know stay in shape
you can certainly spend a day or an hour
or so every day in the gym
let's say 90 minutes a day in the gym I
mean going and coming will take some
time and all but 60 Minutes I did you
can certainly do that and you can stay
really fit in those 60 minutes so you
can do boxing sessions power lifting
sessions weightlifting sessions all that
in the gym you can do that but being an
athlete typically means that you are
doing track and field activities which
take a lot of time so if you want to be
a proper athlete and compete in events
and all that you cannot do that and also
study or have a job at the same time but
you can certainly have a job and go to
gym every day and stay very fit it can
certainly be a student study full-time
and also go to gym every day and stay
fit but you can't have a job and also be
a competitive athlete that's impossible
uh well as far as I can say it's
impossible I'm sure some superhuman
people can do it but for most of us
Ordinary People it's it's more or less
impossible
right okay
okay Vladimir Vladimir putz
Vladimir vladimiro which Putin says guys
create a map of Chinese okay by Tibet I
would exhort all of you to please go
ahead and do that go ahead and do that
and then tag me on Twitter or whatever
or you know we'll find a way of
publicizing these maps please do that
okay
all right
um
the Indian Navy is pushing for a third
aircraft carrier do you think it's a
smart decision I remember you saying
that the Navy should focus more on
submarines and corbetts Etc there is a
logic
that you have to employ
let's take a look at the map
look at the Indian Coastline it's an
enormous coastline
and the area of our interest our
strategic interest is the is the Indian
Ocean region north of the equator all
the way up to the Strait of Malacca all
the way up to the Strait of Hormuz
and all the way to the Gulf of Arden
that's our region of interest it's an
enormous region
so if you have a single enormous ship an
aircraft carrier
it will have a certain
radius of influence
and it's also going to be a place where
you are concentrating all of your
lethality and you're investing a huge
amount of money an aircraft carrier
costs anything between three to ten
billion dollars let's say we go for a
third one which will cost let's say
three to let's say five billion dollars
all in all invested you're gonna put
let's say 50 aircraft on it helicopters
all that stuff there's a whole lot of
investment in just one place
right and there's a whole lot of
lethality in one place it's an
incredibly enticing Target
for the enemy whoever it is and you have
to defend it using lots of other ships
you need to have at least one submarine
patrolling the area you need to have at
least three to four destroyers and a
whole bunch of other ships protecting
the aircraft carrier so it's not just
those five billion dollars worth of
money that you're investing you're
investing much more it's extremely
expensive and what do you get out of it
you can control a certain area but it's
also dangerous
in in the same money if you invest in
let's say 50
different ships of different kinds you
can more effectively control a much
larger area and distribute your
lethality over a much larger
surface area of the ocean does it not
make more sense
I am just talking logically I have
nothing against aircraft carriers I
think they're Majestic
it would be fun to be the captain of an
aircraft carrier it will be like the
greatest
Flex that you could have in the Navy
yeah
but that's not something that serves our
national interests
we already have two let's
so I don't know what the Navy's logic is
okay obviously I have never served in
the Navy or in the armed forces so you
could clear the diamond armchair General
but there is a logic
just the logic of strategy
a lot of the great strategists never
served in the armed forces
one of the great strategists of all time
has been on our Channel Dr Edward
luthwork
he did serve in the in the military in
in his youth uh
so I'm not sure what his opinion is I
think he has also said that we don't
that India should not have more than two
aircraft carriers it's not necessary
that money can be used elsewhere to
distribute our lethality if you have
let's say 50 ships or 100 ships spread
out over a large area how many will you
take out they will all have their own
defenses so it's easier to take out a
single aircraft carrier by by
concentrating a whole let's say hail of
missiles but if you have so many ships
spread out it's very hard to take them
all out and they can always take you out
so it makes sense to have to invest that
money in lots of different kinds of
ships submarines Corvettes destroyers
and whatnot instead of putting
everything in all your eggs in one
basket
so yeah
that is my perspective maybe the Navy
doesn't exist and it doesn't agree agree
with me
okay Pakistani claims that Parini was
born in ancient Pakistan we don't know
exactly where where uh acharya panani
was born he was born in the Indian
subcontinent which was all India at the
time
now
we don't quite know the location maybe
it was the subastu valley which is now
called SWAT which is temporarily part of
Pakistan
so it doesn't matter what see Pakistan
itself is is Indian Territory okay it's
a temporary matter that it's currently
what it is
so
Pakistan did not exist before 1947. so
even if somebody was born in what is now
Pakistani territory before 1947 it
doesn't make that person Pakistani okay
that person was Indian
so you know it's all it's kind of a joke
what these people do
we don't need to take them seriously
right okay what next what next
hush says were there any special
military units in Ancient India like the
Spartans well I am sure we would have
had all kinds of elite military units
and all that but the records of these uh
things are all lost because of the
destruction of our great ancient
libraries so all the records of our
history were burned down by The
Barbarians who did this
so we don't quite know how armies were
organized
what sort of Cavalry we had what sort of
inventory we had what Siege Warfare uh
equipment we had if any
um
mounted Warriors elephant elephant
elephants used in Warfare all those
things what sort of logistical
Arrangements did we have an army runs on
Logistics Logistics is the key to any
military success Logistics is all about
supplies
supplies and communication and all that
that's that's the boring work but that's
what keeps an army in in you know going
so obviously all of this would have
existed Logistics is a very interesting
field and a very complicated field very
hard very difficult
so you're always running into problems
and Logistics but you have to fix them
solve them so we don't know how it was
done because we have lost all the
records of our past so I don't know I
don't have the answer but it's a very
good question you're asking and I'm glad
to see people asking such interesting
questions
all right
um
okay other questions
just a day ago Rolls-Royce the aircraft
engine manufacturer confirmed an export
license for combat engine technology
transfer to the for the amca fighter
will this set the stage for India's
indigenous jet engine production
so I haven't seen this news yet okay I
am this is the first time I'm seeing
this uh so it's what you're saying is
that they confirmed export license for
combat engine technology transfer if
there is
see export license typically means that
you can
they can export something to your
country
that's what it typically means it could
also be interpreted as you can build it
in your country under license and they
will send some kits or whatever you can
assemble it over here and some
components you can manufacture over here
that's the other interpretation when
you're saying technology transfer that
is something that I would imagine that
Rolls-Royce would not want to do because
that technology they have developed over
many decades and why would they transfer
it to another Nation
uh if they're actually doing technology
transfer that's wonderful that's good
for us but I am kind of skeptical about
any such news report
I think that we're gonna have to do it
the hard way maybe work with the French
and maybe pay a huge amount of money for
the technology but eventually we will
have to do it
uh so I don't know what's what quite is
what's quite happening I will look at
the news report and maybe then we can
revisit this part of the thing but it's
an interesting report that you have
brought out over here
okay
um
what else do we have we have lots of
questions
D says I'm a student science student
12th class I want to take advice from
you about for my future profession how
can I do so listen
I can only advise you about what
profession you should take if I know you
personally
only if I know you personally if I know
your likes and dislikes what you're good
at what you're not so good at what your
aptitudes are only when I know you
personally can I give you an actual
advice
so uh so you know the the best thing to
do is to uh
take advice from somebody you actually
already know in person
you know
uh so so that's what what I can tell you
maybe somebody a teacher or a professor
or some Elder person somebody with
experience go to them and tell them that
what your
what your future plans are what your
future hopes and aspirations are and
because they know you personally they'll
be able to guide you much better than me
I would be able to guide you because I
don't really know you right
okay
devange says why is Russia silent on
Finland so Finland has joined NATO isn't
it okay do we know where Finland is
let's go and find Finland on the map
where is the map so we know where India
is then we go westwards into Europe then
we go into northern Europe and we have
the nation of Finland over here here we
are the capital city is Helsinki
Helsinki
and it's quite close to Sanctuary
Petersburg Saint Petersburg
so Finland has recently in the past week
or so if I'm not mistaken joined NATO
officially
so the question is why is Russia silent
on Finland see
what Finland has done
is they've done what they've the thing
has really changed Finland was already
very strongly in the U.S and NATO camp
so this is simply putting the stamp of
finality on that stamp of approval so
now it's official it's it's rubber
stamped but the situation hasn't changed
Finland was already very much part of
the Western Alliance so uh so there's no
point talking about it and Russia
doesn't need to react to it I'm not sure
if they've spoken about this or reacting
to it
um chirag says why doesn't India have
more basal States
India has never been in the past 70 plus
years a powerful Nation
India became a nation-state in 1947.
since then India has pursued a path of
extreme mediocrity because of all
leaders
it's only in the past
let's say decade let's say decade that
India has become a nation that's now
beginning to rise to its potential
but before that it's all been mediocrity
and low standards so when you are a
mediocre Nation when you are not
powerful when your economy is not
growing when you don't have significant
military might
you're not going to have a South States
you will not have a big sphere of
influence and we do not when you don't
have a big sphere of influence beyond
your borders how will you have assault
States it just doesn't make any sense
right does it make any sense so that's
why
and also we don't believe in in you know
we have a certain way of doing things
it's a cultural thing
we don't bully other nations we don't
colonize or occupy Nations and we don't
take Versailles
but let's see how it goes in the future
so that's the reason why historically in
the past let's say two three hundred
years India does not India has not had
basal States you go back to the Chula
times the entirety of Southeast Asia was
our vasala yeah
and uh the kushan times and Gupta times
and all it was all different uh a very
different scenario
okay
what octar says I'm gonna I'm good at
only mathematics I have passed the 12th
standard exam what should I do
well you are facing the kind of dilemma
that that srinivas ramanujan faced he
was good at only maths but he was a
genius at math
uh so listen once again I don't know you
personally so I cannot give you advice I
can give you a very Bland generic advice
that I can give to anybody but that
won't help you
and I can't give you the advice you
really need unless I know you personally
and understand what you're all about so
once again I would say that what you
should do is go and seek out somebody
who is experienced somebody who is
who will
who will care for you and who will want
to take you in the right direction and
take their advice that's what I would
say because without knowing you
personally I really cannot give you the
right advice
all right
um
please
talk
about
Swami
[Music]
uh unfortunately I don't know who that
is
so can't talk about them about about
this person sorry
okay let's see what else what else what
is
should India adopt gun culture for
personal safe safety just like the us
considering the increasing incidence of
clashes among communities listen if you
have an increasing trend
of increasing clashes among communities
first of all I'm not saying that the
trend okay
these clashes or whatever it is these
frictions have always been there but
only now what the thing is that it's all
coming out on social media it's always
been there I'm not saying it's a good
thing or a bad thing I'm just saying
it's it's always been there not always
but for a long time
uh
so should India adopt gun culture let's
say you have tensions between two
communities three communities whatever
and they don't have guns so whatever if
at all any violence happens it's gonna
be limited to a certain kind of thing
but imagine now everybody has guns
imagine what can happen
so I think the answer is not that
everybody should have guns that's not
the answer the answer is better policing
better better uh enforcement of the laws
and and the rule of the law that's what
needs to happen
gun culture is not going to help anybody
gun culture is very dangerous
so we know what happens in the U.S every
other day there's an active shooter
somewhere it's terrible it's tragic
tragic what's happened to the to the
nation
that's what they've done to themselves
unfortunately it's very tragic
okay
ayushman Singh says why did America not
nuke Tokyo I am not sure if they had
plans of nuking Doki or not
um so I think they bombed the nuked
Hiroshima first in the Nagasaki as a
means of warning
the Japanese government let's look this
is what we can do to you and if you
don't surrender maybe Tokyo is next so
I'm not sure if they had made plans to
Nuke Tokyo but they certainly had the
ability
so maybe they wanted see when you uh
defeat a nation and when you take over a
nation you want to take it as much
intact as possible you don't want to
take over a nation that is flattened and
destroyed
yeah so it makes sense to leave it as
undamaged as possible
and when you take over a nation
think from the perspective of an Invader
a colonizer
when you take over a nation you want a
ready-made
system
that will now serve you so if you
destroy Tokyo all the bureaucracy in the
government Machinery will be destroyed
then you will have to train people and
set it up all over again which is a very
tedious long and time time consuming
procedure
so
that also makes sense and that's also
could be that also could be a reason why
they did not need to care maybe they
kept it for later and they did not have
to ever use it so these are the
possibilities I'm not really sure if
they had plans of new king Tokyo maybe
they did perhaps I mean it would make
sense for them to have such a plan
all right
um
can India survive AI technology
digitally colonizing our businesses and
dictate terms as West owns most of the
AI Rajiv Malhotra says so please answer
uh
I think India could certainly do very
well in AI uh all the AI startups all
the AI companies everything that's
available online it's all Western It's
All American chat GPT open AI is
American uh Bard Google CI is also
American uh we also have Bing AI which
is also American so all these AI
companies Etc they are all American and
obviously if you rely on them entirely
it's gonna end up uh yeah you could say
digitally colonizing your nation so
India obviously has extremely talented
people I'm sure many of the people who
are working in this AI companies and
startups are of Indian origin right in
the US
so India has no shortage of 300 people
but uh
the question is why does India not
produce the next Google or the next
Facebook the next Twitter next Instagram
or the next chat GPT that's the question
right I think Indian business people are
very risk averse and they want to put
money in a very safe thing
they don't want to
do a lot of r d which is risky and you
may lose money it takes time they want
to see Returns on their investment
immediately that's why nobody is
investing in these speculative Ventures
look AI three years ago was completely
speculative right you could train all
these neural networks with enormous
amounts of data but we don't you know
you did not know what's going to happen
you could be optimistic and you could
hope for your your the way you're doing
things go well but maybe you want to
lose all the time and all that money so
these things are risky the biggest
rewards come from taking risks so India
can certainly
you know create its own AI systems
we have data we have a huge amount of
data ourselves but we don't quite
leverage it
so if things continue the way they are
continuing then yeah India could get
digitally colonized by the West so we
have to be aware of this and hopefully
somebody starts an Indian air company or
multiple Indian air companies that will
be great
because the one thing that you also see
uh if you use these AI systems is what I
have spoken about a very long time ago
like two years ago or something I think
no there is I don't think I know for a
fact that on this channel there is a
clip
of me answering a question about
algorithm bias so there is something
called algorithmic bias which I have
gone into detail about In that clip so
we are actually already seeing algorithm
bias in some of the answers that these
AI systems uh give you you know they are
trained to do certain things they are
constrained in certain ways and the
answers they give are you could if you
know how to you know where to look okay
you can see you can tell that there is a
bias implicit in all this and that's
because of the kind of data these AI
systems were fed when they were trained
so yeah so India needs to you know
ensure it's not left behind in the AI
race
okay
asks a very interesting question
the princely state of kalath Balochistan
after Independence wanted to join India
and not Pakistan and India asked Oman
asked India to have guadar so why did we
refuse wasn't it a strategic land
yeah well you're right
the Khan of Kala the last Khan of khalaf
wanted khalas to exceed to India not to
Pakistan and kalathism is a significant
portion of Balochistan so essentially
the Khan of was
the de facto ruler of Balochistan itself
so he wanted khalat or Balochistan to
exceed to India to become a part of
India
and Oman wanted India to have godar
and what happened is that we got neither
godar nor Balochistan we gave it all up
and we refused the Balochi request to
accede to India and we refused the Khan
of uh the the sultana's offer
to
to take
so why did we do it that's a question
that we need a detailed explanation it
will take at least 20 or 25 minutes to
bring out all the patterns but what I
can tell you is that the great Shri
jawaharlal nehru made these choices and
there are no real logical explanations
for these choices makes no sense
whatsoever
but yeah he did that
okay
what other questions do we have
um
Aditya says what's quantum entanglement
in Hawking radiation let's take the
second one first what's Hawking
radiation so we all think of black holes
as this giant vacuum cleaners that suck
everything in right but uh
if you uh study black holes properly you
will see that black holes have a
temperature there is black holes uh
black holes have a number of properties
Mass charge and angular momentum these
are the three intrinsic properties that
a black hole can have and black holes
also have temperature it's called the
Hawking temperature
and because they have a temperature they
radiate
so that's that's in very brief what the
Hawking radiation is so black holes
aren't dark they actually radiate a flux
of particles depending on the
temperature so if it's a small the
smaller black hole is the hotter it is
and the more it will radiate when the
larger a black hole is is the colder it
is and the less it will radiate and
supermassive black holes depending on
the size will could actually end up
being colder than the cosmic microwave
background radiation temperature which
means that they will not radiate they
will accrete and they're really really
dark they are genuinely dark so uh that
is what Hawking Edition is it is the
phenomenon by which black holes radiate
quantum entanglement is a
it's it's where you have so let me give
you a very you know crude analogy
entanglement so it's when two particles
are connected
in such a way that they actually form a
single system so let's say you have one
particle that is over here in my in this
room and you have one particle which has
reached the Andromeda galaxy let's say
many hundreds maybe thousands millions
of light years away from here
and yet those particles are still
connected to each other
and if you you see one particle and
measure its properties will immediately
instantaneously know the properties of
the other particle which is like light
years away
so it's spooky action at a distance
faster than light travel of information
looks like it appears like it is so but
it's not quite quite that it is what it
is
so what do you mean by entangled
particles so think of it like this I buy
a pair of gloves
okay a left-handed glove and the
right-handed glove and I put them in
different boxes you know I close my eyes
I shuffle the gloves together then take
one glove put in one box and take
another glove and put in the other box I
like close the boxes seal them off and I
send one box to my friend in Tokyo
and I send the other box to my friend in
Paris
okay
now I don't know which went where and
neither do the recipients but when my
friend in Tokyo opens the box and let's
say finds that it's a left-handed glove
then that person will immediately know
that the person in Paris has a right in
it love right and let's say instead of
Tokyo in Paris I send one to Mars and I
send one
to the Andromeda Galaxy
so my Martian friend when he or she or
it will open the glove and it sees one
love let's say it's a right-handed glove
he or she or it will know immediately
that the one in Andromeda is the other
one so that's the kind of thing that's
that's a very crude way of explaining
what entanglement is so when two
particles are entangled they have the
same uh they form they are the same
system and they are the the wave
foreign
function that I mean I'm not sure if it
makes sense to you but that's what it is
so that's what quantum entanglement is
it's a phenomenon that happens at the
ultra microscopic hyper microscopic
level the subatomic level
all right
next what do we have
we have all kinds of other questions
okay let's take this one sun shades one
says we know about D dollarization how
fast do you think it will happen it has
been in the news a lot these days your
thoughts the dollarization you know it's
easier said than done the dollar is the
world's has been the world's region of
Reserve currency for a very very long
time lots and lots of decades ever since
1944 if I think if I if I remember
remember correctly the Britain Woods
agreement and all the conference and all
that
and the US is still the most powerful
nation in the world its influence may be
decreasing but its power hasn't
decreased so yeah of course they are
doing all these stupid things like
printing enormous amounts of money over
one weekend the printed 300 billion
dollars of worth of money just created
money out of thin air because they own
the currencies so they can do whatever
they want
and clearly there is a trend there is a
desire among nations Saudi Arabia Iran
India
the UAE China Russia Etc to move away
from the US dollar because if you trade
only in dollars and you deal only in
dollars then the Americans can control
everything and they can cut you off from
the system anytime they want and they
can destroy your economy but if you are
not using the dollar then it's
impossible essentially for the Americans
to do that and we have seen what the
Americans have done in recent times to
Iran to Yemen and in the latest instance
to Russia you know they cut Russia off
from the Swift system the International
Financial system and they impose those
times in Russia but Russia has been able
to withstand and those sanctions and do
reasonably well but imagine if it
happens to your country you don't want
that to happen so it makes sense to move
away from the dollar
and use other currencies so India is now
entering into agreement with a whole lot
of Nations
uh for using the rupee
as the currency of exchange for various
uh
uh transfers of
value we also have the Saudis agreeing
to you to trade in the in the Yuan we
have the rupee Ruble agreement and so on
so it's a process that's happening
slowly
uh I don't see it happening very rapidly
in the dollar dollar going out of
business anytime soon but yes there is
definitely a trend to move away from the
US dollar and that Trend May gather
steam as time goes by
kaushik says your thoughts on UFO or UAP
and why India is not researching this
phenomenon well unfortunately you don't
see UFOs and Indian Skies
these UFOs or UAP un on whatever aerial
phenomena they only seem to happen in
the U.S
the only thing seem to bless the US with
their presence
uh I can't remember see nowadays
everybody in India has cell phones
everybody has video cameras so how come
nobody is witnessing such things in it
or in over Indian Skies
so we don't see any UFO footage or or
images coming out of India
if it is there it must be very rare So
if it's not happening here how do we
research it should we send our
scientists to the to the us so that they
can witness this phenomena over there it
seems to happen all the time so you know
so that's the reason it doesn't happen
here so the aliens if they exist they
only want to come to the U.S
uh what what sense did it make tell me
okay
all right let's see what else
Grim so bad says how to cope with
Society for forcing you to follow the
norms and force you to stay on the safe
side
yeah well you've got to take risks of
course you can't take stupid risks you
need to First learn risk management by
taking very small risks and see how
seeing how it goes so a bad example
perhaps would be the stock market
example you could let's say you have a
bank balance bank account balance of
let's say one lakh rupees okay just a
hypothetical example so you what's the
example of big risk you take all the
money and put it into stocks and you
don't have any experience so you you
essentially gambling that's a big risk
what you can actually do is you instead
of taking the one lakh rupees use you
invest a thousand rupees every month in
various stocks and see how it performs
and you do it for the next three years
keep on investing a thousand rupees a
month that's not a big amount of money
in that way you will be able to gain a
lot of experience and see how various
stocks perform so that's how you do risk
management you learn it unfortunately we
don't we're not taught these things in
school so yes Society will force you the
society will want you to stay in a
certain Lane
Society wants you to be average be like
everybody else do what everybody else
does take the safe job
you know do the same things
so clearly you you're not happy with
that you want you want to be different
so there seems to be something inside
you that says that I want to be
different I want to be better
exceptional whatever it is so
if you want to be different it's
certainly worthwhile but it's not easy
it's a hard path
and yeah people will try to dissuade you
people will try to make it difficult for
you people will make fun of you
especially if you don't succeed
immediately people will make fun of you
people very close to you will do that to
you so it's not easy but you know the
great people they're all different they
all took the path that other people
don't take
so how to do it you have to first become
mentally very strong
emotionally very strong we Indians are
ruled by emotions we are very emotional
people so we have to put the emotions
aside emotions have a place in life but
not everywhere you don't need to make
everything all about emotions so you
have to find a way of becoming mentally
strong
and you have to know what path You Want
To Tread and then you have to follow the
path and do it properly take risks but
not enormous risks and that's how we do
it
so that's what I can tell you in a
generic manner because I don't know
exactly what your you know likes
dislikes aptitudes are but yeah
you have to find your own way that's
what it is
okay
what should I do since do I do business
or join the Indian army as an officer to
contribute to the country most I am good
at business and I'm 19. you should do
what you are good at
there are 1.4 billion people in the
country
I'm sure millions of them are really
good at fighting many millions of them
are good at strategy and tactics let
those guys who really love it who are
made for it let them go into the Armed
Forces in case you are better at
something else then you should pursue
that in case you're really good at
fighting and you're really good at
Fitness and you're really strong and
tall and you are you have a good
strategic Outlook and all that then you
should go for the Army for sure because
you're good at that but if you're
already good at business and you know
that go for business and contribute to
the economy in that manner you know
create jobs create products do all that
so do whatever you're best at that's
what I would tell you
okay
can we trust press and journalism no you
can't you cannot
I'm sure there are some journalists out
of 100 maybe there are two or three
journalists who are entirely completely
100 percent uh honest
and I'm sure that out of 100 at least 50
journalists will be good people
but even if you're a good person
you are still
doing a job and you are paid by someone
you have a boss
you have an employer
and when you are paid by that person or
by that organization you have to do what
what is expect what they expect of you
if you disagree
with whatever they want you to do then
you should not be on their payroll
and for most people you know it's
important to have a steady steady income
so journalism has become that sort of
thing you know people used to believe
that journalism is this Noble Endeavor
and it's all about truths and all that
it's not the case Okay most news
is
well it's agenda driven most news
actually is propaganda most journalism
is peddling various kinds of narratives
and propaganda
so
like I said disclaimer that some people
will be good but overall the majority of
it is like that so you cannot trust the
press and you cannot trust news reports
and most journalism Please be aware of
this
Suraj Kumar says I have no money for
Super Chat well I'm not asking you for
money I don't superchar is turned off
right
so yeah I I I turned off Super Chat like
I had tried it a few times
but uh what I found is that many of the
people many of the viewers over here on
the channel are kids youngsters you know
students and I've been a student we've
all been there when you're a student
you're a when you are a student you're
broke you don't have any money of your
own so how can you expect students to to
pay money to ask to to have the question
answered so I realized this very early
and I turned off Super Chat maybe once
or twice I may have turned it on just
just to see how it goes but uh on this
channel there is no Super Chat you don't
have to uh pay me money to ask me
questions please that is that is
horrific I I don't believe in that
all right
more questions oh we already did one one
hour 50 minutes Mark wonderful
good God how to
how to stop having suicidal thoughts I
um I have no idea
because I've now been there I would say
please consult talk to your eldest
consult a psychiatrist psychologist
whatever it is and get some help okay
get professional help
I have no idea what would cause such
things
one would imagine it would be depression
or something like that or something else
I I know I am not an authority in this
field if you have such a thing please
immediately
consult a professional okay and and
please talk to your family talk to your
elders talk to whoever you trust and
please take professional help that's
what I would say
all the best all the best please get
well
okay some other questions let's see
Kelly says Kelly
says why does no one see Russia as the
next superpower and why do people think
that China and India are the only
Nations that can surpass Big Daddy Big
Daddy USA in the geopolitical game
see we know at what rate India is
growing China is growing economically
and Russia is growing Russia's economy
is not growing
anywhere close to the the kind of
economic growth China had in the past
and the kind of growth India is having
right now so economically Russia is not
slated is not in a position because of
simple mathematics it's not in a
position to surpass the US in this
century
the the Chinese also see what's
happening to their economy
their economy is Contracting
that GDP growth is is has been negative
in recent times
and even if it starts growing again
it'll be like two percent three percent
per year maximum four or five percent if
at all
so China is based on the trends and
Simple Pure math China is no longer in a
position
[Music]
to ever surpass the US in this Century
economically by the end of the century
China's population will be half of what
it is today and the average age will be
most likely in excess of 60. imagine the
average person around you is 60 years
old
that's the situation China is going to
face it's already getting there slowly
so China is not going to surpass the U.S
Russia well Russia has the world's
largest military uh nuclear Arsenal and
it has this enormous territory which
makes it an otaki and otaki is a nation
that's completely self-sufficient in all
basic things all basic necessities
resources you know Metals iron ore coal
natural gas petroleum agriculture all
the basic stuff that you need to run an
economy everything is there so Russia is
really blessed from that perspective but
it's not growing economically and its
population is also slowly declining you
know so Russia faces that problem China
faces and even more uh drastic problem
and the only nation that's
projected or capable
of surpassing the U.S economically in
this century is India that's the only
nation right so Russia I would say it is
not quite a superpower but it's the it's
a great power
purely based on the kind of resources it
has and also because it has the world's
largest nuclear Arsenal and the missiles
and all the capability to deploy and
deliver those those nuclear weapons
whenever they want
as much as we talk about Pakistan
occupied Kashmir
well exceptionism Chinese hands and for
the longest time we Indians thought of
the Chinese as invincible
because we have heard about 1962 well we
are not taught what happened in 1967
there was another war between India and
China and we defeated the Chinese in
that in 1987 also The sundarong Chew
clashes and all that we got the better
of that
so um but we but your teachers won't
teach you that your history textbooks
will not write about it the media will
not talk about it so you will not know
about this and you will keep having this
inferiority complex that China is you
know invincible
so I think that's the reason why nobody
talks about Sachin because people feel
in India that you can't take anything
from China it's just impossible China is
just two just too powerful too strong so
that's why we talk about Pok all the
time I get 17 28 questions per day at
least about when are we going to take
back P okay but nobody asks about
exciting I think that's the reason why
because we have this image that's been
created in our minds that China is
invincible and India is no match for
China which is
complete fiction but yeah that's why
okay let's see what else do we have
ramai Raj Singh says need a definitive
answer was Lord Ram a non-vegetarian
have sanatanis being non-vegetarians or
is this a written recent pickup listen
um
I don't know
I don't know and if I answer one way or
the other it's gonna create a
controversy and I'm gonna get a whole
lot of hate
so listen I don't know we have the
incident of Lord drama you know hunting
a deer because lady Sita wanted the
deer's skin but then people have all
kinds of esoteric interpretations of
that
that uh that children would not want
drama to kill the deer she just wanted
Lord Ram to bring the deer back so that
she could play with it that's when
interpretation people give so you know I
maybe they are right maybe maybe what we
believe is wrong I don't know so my
answer is I don't know
Lord Rama was a king he was a chatriya
chatriyas typically have been
non-vegetarian but who knows you know in
the old days maybe they were not but
when you are a warrior
you need a good source of protein and
meat is the easiest sort of protein but
then when you say such things it really
offends people and people get upset so
my answer is gonna be that I don't know
you know I I just don't know what about
people of India have there been
non-vegetarians or is this a really
recent thing I think in India India is a
subcontinent sized piece of geography
you will always have a huge amount of
diversity of Cuisine of of dietary
choices and all that
so it's it's India has never been a
single monolithic monochromatic uniform
ethnic group right we are bound together
by one civilizational heritage
it's the civilization and culture that
binds us together but otherwise of the
cultural diversity is immense so you you
have people
in India today who are purely vegetarian
and who follow the same culture and you
have people in other parts of India who
will eat fish but they considered that
to be vegetarian then there are some
people in other parts of India who eat
other kinds of meat so it's a very
diverse place so I think Indians overall
have valued non-violence in
vegetarianism but there have always been
as far as I can understand Indians in
various parts of India here or there who
have eaten meat
all right let's take two three more
questions
okay let's see
what do I think about the Tate Brothers
I really don't know much about the Tate
Brothers they are very controversial
very much in the news and they have very
strong opinions and they are like
leading what they call the manosphere or
whatever it is I don't quite know I have
never watched a single podcast or
interview of one of the Tate guys Andrew
trade is it
and uh I I've I've heard I know what the
reputation is like you know very strong
opinions and masculinity and uh
they are accused of being misogynistic
and worse things as well so my answer is
I don't quite know because I've never
really had much of an interest in who
these people were
so yeah I don't quite know you know
but yeah it's it's good that we
discussed this about what's what's
happening these days over here around
the world
okay ISRO
Ani says ISRO and NASA have said that
due to global warming the coastal cities
like Mumbai Goa Kolkata Etc and other
coastal cities in the world like Tokyo
and so on so forth
uh by 20 30 20 50 means you mean they'll
go under the water
how much of this is true listen climate
change has always existed so climate
change is real anyone who claims climate
change doesn't exist is uh well
climate change has always been there
ever since our planet was born the
climate has been changing now obviously
the climate is changing now as well and
obviously some of it is man-made so
there is a human-made component to the
climate change that we are witnessing
now
now if you look at photographs of the
Statue of Liberty in New York taken a
hundred years ago and if you take
photographs today the sea level is the
same
the global warming has been happening
where the sea level is the same
so uh I'm not saying that is this means
that the sea levels won't rise in the in
the future sea levels have varied a lot
in the past
I mean about 10 000 years ago the sea
levels were about 150 150 meters below
where they are right now so sea levels
will rise and fall and right now we have
definitely witnessing a period of
warming and in a trend of warming every
year little bit little bit more
so from that perspective it makes sense
that sea levels will indeed rise over
time
so I don't know when it will happen
maybe by 2050 I don't think I don't
think you will see significant degrees
by 2030. but yeah you may see changes by
2050 possibly so we don't quite know and
let's it's still um you know predicting
these things is still a very
the predictions aren't very accurate
because our science our understanding of
Science in our modeling Etc it will not
be that good thus far
but yeah global warming is indeed a
thing sea levels will overall rise over
time how much and how much time we don't
quite know but yeah some rise will
happen
by 2050 possibly possibly
okay let me take one more question and
then we are done for the day because
it's already two hours plus
um
how can India develop soft power like I
said the by doing good things soft power
is your reputation
you know your reputation which comes
from your entertainment industry from
your culture uh from your sporting
performance
from how rich
or prosperous you are all these things
so the key to developing soft power is
to develop the economy which also
develops your heart power
right
okay I said I'll take one more question
I will take one more question can a star
exist without emitting any light ah no
no
Stars radiate lots and lots of
electromagnetic radiation which is
called light which is photons and
yeah you could have hypothetical dark
stars made up of dark matter it depends
on what what dark matter is made of
let's imagine it's just purely
gravitating particles that interact only
gravitationally and yeah if you bring
sufficient numbers of particles together
it will form a very huge mass and it
could actually ignite under its own
weight
it's interesting yeah dark stars they
may still be dark but they may read it
in the gravitational Spectrum but yeah
that's that's purely conjecture and
hypothetical stuff but uh apart from
that I would say that a star cannot
exist without emitting any light because
otherwise it would not be a star at all
yeah all right I guess we are done for
the day do I see anybody else
how do one gain confirm confirm what I'm
not quite sure what you're asking
confirm
yeah I'm I'm not sure I got I got what
what this means
sorry
um
let's see yeah I took the Stars question
there are a million other questions
um
Let Me Maybe take one more question
someone says
what was the original original purpose
behind alcohol except for entertainment
I I don't know what's the purpose of all
behind alcohol except for using it as a
recreational drug
I mean when a person brings alcohol it
impairs the nervous system and causes a
different kind of behavior right you're
not quite in control of what you're
doing your your your speech isn't normal
your words will be slurred your control
over the body is not the same you know
Drunken Master fighting in boxing it
kind of imitates the style so I think
it's it's just a recreational drug
It's Entertainment it doesn't really
have any health benefits or any such
thing
okay
I guess okay
teaching says how do you gain confidence
how do you gain confidence
you gain confidence by
through practice let's say you want to
become
let's just take the example of sport you
want to get good at playing a certain
sport or let's say yeah sport let's say
so how do you do how do you build the
confidence if I'm good by practicing
practicing practicing investing hours
and hours and hours and doing it so many
times over and over again that it
becomes second nature then you're
confident let's say you want to talk
about public speaking for instance
another another example well the first
time you're gonna go in face up face a
number of people and give a speech it's
gonna be frightening for you so you're
going to start small maybe you should
start by practicing in front of the
mirror or practicing in front of front
of your phone camera and do it over and
over again let's let's say you do it for
20 days
three weeks then you get used to talking
then maybe you can build a con you will
feel that yeah maybe I can talk to two
or three people then you go and do it in
front of three people and you do it for
a few days then you will feel like yeah
I can do it in front of 10 people now so
you it is you do it in stages
but the thing is that you have to put in
the hard work if you put in the hard
work the effort then it becomes second
nature for you and you become confident
so whatever field or skill you want to
develop confidence in you have to dive
into it and do lots of repetitions lots
of repetitions over and over again keep
on doing it keep on doing it keep on
practicing and then it is impossible for
you to not become confident
and oral is a person how do you be
confident some people are just overall
confident right so it's by
acquiring valuable skills
and
being able to genuinely contribute
something to society
and how do you know that somebody is has
valuable skills and is contributing
typically they'll be rich because if you
have valuable skills and you're
contributing those skills to society
then Society rewards you by giving you
money
but typically such people who are
Achievers are they end up being rich and
then if you feel that it is to be
confident you to be rich but it's the
other way around
yeah so it's it's about that you have to
be a valuable person for society and you
provide some value
and you have high value skills
and you're really good at that that will
automatically give you confidence
so that's
that's how you approach it okay I guess
we are done for today all right so thank
you very much everybody for all the
questions tomorrow I am not going to do
a live stream because I'm traveling but
as you can see now the channel is is
going in a certain certain direction and
uh new videos are coming out every day
with some editing and stuff and it's
going to continue so please enjoy the
videos on the channel I will see you in
the next live stream which will
hopefully be in some time around the
next weekend so until then take care and
I will catch you very soon take care all
of you see you soon bye good night good
day bye